<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of housebandrie No lesse profitable then delectable: declaryng how by the housebandrie, or rather housewiferie of Hennes, for fiue hundred frankes or Frenche poundes (makyng Englishe money lv.pi.xi.s̄.i.d.) once emploied, one maie gaine in the yere fower thousande and fiue hundreth frankes (whiche in Englishe money, maketh fiue hundreth poundes) of honest profite: all costes and charges deducted. Written in the Frenche tongue by Maister Prudens Choiselat. And lately translated into Englishe by R.E.</title>
            <title>Discours oeconomique non moins utile que recreatif. English.</title>
            <author>Prudent Le Choyselat, M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10176</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100870</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836697</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836697</idno>
            <idno type="VID">982</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10176)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 982)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1183:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of housebandrie No lesse profitable then delectable: declaryng how by the housebandrie, or rather housewiferie of Hennes, for fiue hundred frankes or Frenche poundes (makyng Englishe money lv.pi.xi.s̄.i.d.) once emploied, one maie gaine in the yere fower thousande and fiue hundreth frankes (whiche in Englishe money, maketh fiue hundreth poundes) of honest profite: all costes and charges deducted. Written in the Frenche tongue by Maister Prudens Choiselat. And lately translated into Englishe by R.E.</title>
                  <title>Discours oeconomique non moins utile que recreatif. English.</title>
                  <author>Prudent Le Choyselat, M.</author>
                  <author>R. E., fl. 1580.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Jhon [sic] Kyngston, for Myles Jennynges dwellyng in S. Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of M. Prudent Le Choyselat: Discours oeconomique non moins utile que recreatif.</note>
                  <note>Another edition of STC 20452, published in 1577.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chicken industry --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:982:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:982:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A DISCOVRSE Of Houſebandrie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No leſſe profitable then delectable: declaryng</hi> how by the Houſebandrie, or rather <hi>Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiferie of Hennes, for fiue hundred Frankes or Frenche</hi> poundes (makyng Engliſhe money lv. li. xj. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i.d.) once emploied, one maie gaine in the yere fower thouſande and fiue hundreth Frankes (whiche in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe money, maketh fiue hundreth poundes) of honeſt profite: all coſtes and charges deducted.</p>
            <p>Written in the Frenche tongue by Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Prudens Choiſelat.</hi> And late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traſlated into Engliſhe by <hi>R. E.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>¶ Jmprinted at London by Jhon Kyngston, for Myles Jennynges dwellyng in S. Paules Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Bible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>1580.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="rate_of_exchange">
            <pb facs="tcp:982:2"/>
            <p>A Souſe, if twelue Frenche pence.</p>
            <p>Xij. Souſe maketh a Frenche Teſton, whiche is fower grotes. Engliſhe.</p>
            <p>Three Souſes, make a grote.</p>
            <p>A Franke or Frenche pounde, is twentie Souſes, xviij. Souſes make twoo ſhillynges, after nine Souſes to a ſhillyng. So remaineth of the Franke twoo Souſes to make vp the Franke of twentie Souſes.</p>
            <p>Nine Frenche pence, make one Engliſhe penie, nine Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, one ſhillyng: nine Frankes one Engliſhe pounde: nine hundreth, one hundreth: nine thouſande, one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:982:2"/>
            <head>To the right honorable the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>Rotchfort, knight of the order of the <hi>Kyng, and capitainc of fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi> menne of Armes of his <hi>Ordinaunces.</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y lorde, hauyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my youth in memorie the precepte of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles, moſte excellent Painter of his tyme, who commaunded his Prentices not to paſſe one daie, without drawyng of a line, to the ende to keepe them in breath and continuance (as doth the Hunter his Greybound) he ſemeth by that precept to ſhewe how greate idleneſſe is to bee auoided, and how greate is the loſſe of tyme, to leaue the exerciſe of trauaill. And therefore, not to tranſgreſſe this precepte in theſe tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and turbulente tymes, compoſed of more then ciuill warres in the bowells of Fraunce, J haue addreſſed my ſelf for the auoidyng of J<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleneſſe, to drawe my line vpon an humble and lowe ſubiect, to make a diſcourſe of domesticall Houſbandrie, and to ſhe we how a diligent man maie of one little ſomme, drawe greate gaines by honest meanes. VVhich doyng, J greately
<pb facs="tcp:982:3"/>recreate my ſpirites emong my bookes, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a greate part of my ſorrowfull thoughtes of theſe troublous tymes. And for aſmuche as J knowe, that after long practiſe of Armes, and the greate trauaile whiche you haue had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the trauaill of letters ſhalbee greatly delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto you, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with equall paſe, you ioyne wiſedome with magnanimitie, I haue taken vpon me the boldneſſe, to preſent vnto you this my little labour, by the readyng whereof you maie take one hower of recreation. I haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed this little Houſbandrie in ſutche order that the practiſe beyng therein well instructed in buiyng, and conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thynges bought, with diſcrete distribution of the ſame, maie aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hymſelf to lacke no merchantes. This little diſcourſe, is of the tyme of the troubles of the yere 1567. before that the winde Caecias drew the Cloude of troubles into the Countries of Poictu and Lodunoys, where I appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the marchant to make his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploit, as ſhalbe ſeen in the readyng.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours moste obeiſant, Prudent Choyſelat.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:982:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Aucthour to his freende</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with the troubles of the Ciuill <hi>warres in Fraunce, in the yere</hi> of our Lorde, M.D.LXVII.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He calamities and encombran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the miſeries and ſorrowes, whiche proceede of the inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, into the which the people of this time is plonged in this age of Iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (of Iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I maie ſaie, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened to miſfortune) hath well witneſſed vnto vs, how true is the auncient Prouerbe, whiche ſaith: That <hi>Iupiter</hi> is ſlowe to viſite the ſkinne of the Gote: Yet that in fine, he permitteth not an euill facte vnpuniſhed. Wee haue ſeen with our eyes, and felte by effecte in our Fraunce, at the riſyng of theſe Iaſte troubles, fallyng vpon vs like tempeſt of Haile vnlooked for. The whiche, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng out of the Boxe of <hi>Pandora,</hi> or out of the broſten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected priſon, was ſo ſpred emong men, and hath made ſuch ouerture of vice and miſcheef, that all ſortes of euill are ſette at libertie. <hi>Mars</hi> the Executor of the wrathe of the goddes hath vomited his Eholour without meaſure, that the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng thereof hath chafed them, not onely to ſociall warres, but to all Deuiliſhe attemptes, more then <hi>Megariqu,</hi> to Robberies and Murthers, and (as ſaieth <hi>Cicero</hi>) to <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lariſmes</hi> and moſte cruell inhumanities. <hi>Vulcan</hi> leauyng his proper Region, hath followed theſe miſeries, and ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched theſe habitations, to exerciſe theſe operations: In ſuche ſorte that it is eaſie to Iudge, that theſe miſhappes are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
<pb facs="tcp:982:4"/>emong menne, to put them in memorie of their ſynnes, founde in the ſaied Goates ſkinne, of the whiche you haue paied your lotte: as I haue knowne by the complaintes, whiche you haue made for your greate loſſes of money, and menage ſpoiled and deſtroied by ſackcage, and pillage alſo of your Nobles. In the whiche I lament your fortune, as a common Shipwracke: but pacience muſt ſurmount. And to help you, I haue none other meane then by aduiſe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile: you knowe that all my life, I haue ſpent little tyme in hourdyng of richeſſe, and thynges caduke. And that rather I tooke pleaſure to contente my Spirites, in readyng and ſearchyng of ſutche thinges, as fewe men haue founde. Yet not to refuſe the help of a freend in neceſſitie: and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng that there yet remaineth vnto you, fiue or ſixe hundred Frankes, whiche you haue hidden, forſeyng ſo greate a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance, it ſeemeth vnto me, to the ende that you in nothyng diminiſhe your ſtate of liuyng, ſo to redreſſe the ſame, that you maie eaſely in ſhorte tyme, reenter into as greate and ample reuenewes, as you had before the ſaied troubles.</p>
            <p>Your reuenewe doubtleſſe, conſiſteth in Houſbandrie of all ſortes of cattell, as Beeues, Kine, Mares, Shepe, foule, and ſutche other thinges as reioyſeth them, whiche are giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the countrey life. I can be a witneſſe how your table was euer readie for your familiar freendes: And your wife and daughter were of worſhipfull eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of carefull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion for your familie, entertained by honeſte ſparyng and frugalitie, requiſite in due tyme and ſeaſon. At whiche time alſo you were well eſtemed, for your liberalitie toward your neighbours and freendes. But ſeeyng that Fortune hath courned her viſage (as ſhe is accuſtomed to dooe, when the tyme agreeth with her) you muſt needes retire, and not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer her to remaine with you in like regarde as before. And therefore you muſt forget thoſe loſſes, and thinke of a gaine to come: to the whiche you ſhall attaine eaſely, with this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb facs="tcp:982:4"/>ſomme remainyng, if you will emploie it, as I will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe you. And this without ſpott of villanie, or filthie and exceſſiue gaines. Furthermore, your Houſebandrie ſhall floriſhe, and your name ſhalbee more knowne in Fraunce, then was emong the Greekes, the name of hym that burnte the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> in <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to make no longer diſcourſe: aduiſe your ſelf to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe your ſomme of money in buiyng of Hennes: not <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagrides,</hi> the whiche <hi>Bellonius</hi> in his Peregrination affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, to be our Hennes of the Indies (beyng the true Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers of Otes) but common Hennes of our Countrie: and Houſebande or employe them in ſuche ſort, as I will ſhewe hereafter. And be not impacient to attende the concluſion.</p>
            <p>Firſte of all, it is neceſſarie to haue them, neare vnto the Citée of Paris, famous and of greate renoume throughout all the worlde, to bee the marte and ſeate of all good Artes, and Sciences, and populous of all ſortes of men, if there be any other vnder the Sunne. There conſider the ſituation of ſome commodious place well builded, hauyng good roomes and Stabies, with a Court or yarde incloſed of twoo Acres of grounde, more or leſſe, and walled of ſufficiente height. With alſo twoo other Acres incloſed, for an other purpoſe, whereof we will ſpeake hereafter. Of theſe are enow to be founde, in the old rurall buildynges about the Citie of Paris. So then can you not ſaie, that you are ſtraightly lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. For <hi>Quintus Cincinnatus</hi> Citezine of Rome (ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for wearyng his heire combed and breaded) poſſeſſed no more when he was called to the dignitie of <hi>Dictator,</hi> as writeth <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> in his fowerth booke.</p>
            <p>The aforeſaid Mannour place or Ferme, with Yard or Courte incloſed, you ſhall take by Leaſe for certaine yeres, paiyng yerely rent for the dwelling of you and your familie. You ſhall diſpoſe your Stables commodiouſlie, for your Hennes and Chickins, with the vewe or proſpecte toward
<pb facs="tcp:982:5"/>the Winter Driente, that the Sunne maie giue the good morrowe to your He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, whiche greatly delite at the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng Sunne, as noteth <hi>Columella</hi> in his nineth booke of Houſebandrie: alſo <hi>Varro</hi> in his third booke.</p>
            <p>The Henne houſes, ſhalbe commodious and profitable, if thei bee alone or ſolitarie, and the Plankes well couered with claye, becauſe the Hennes delite to pruine and toum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them ſelues in duſte, and to bee kept warme. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bodrdes or plaiſter, are not conuenient to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The Lathers, or Perches muſt be from the ground two foote high. Alſo flat, and not round, becauſe the Hennes doe not bende, or crooke their clawes or Talantes, as doe other graſpelyng foules.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Henne houſes alſo, in the daie tyme muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that thei maie bee euented with winde and Aire. And that the night aire maie more eaſely tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpire and breath out, that it maie cauſe no diſeaſe by cloſe ayre, whiche in ſhorte time cauſeth putrefaction, and diſeaſes thereof procedyng.</p>
            <p>Vnder the Henne houſes, and all about the ſtables ſhall he hanged many Panyers of conuement bigneſſe, ſtuft with Haye, to receiue the Hennes when thei laye. For Haye in this caſe, is mutche better then Strawe, becauſe it is ſofter and warmer, and is not ſo apt to engender Lice or Woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. I doe not meane that it ſhould be ſo deare as was that whiche was ſold for fower <hi>Attiques</hi> the handfull, for men to eate, at the tyme of the greate Famine in Ieruſalem, as writeth <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his ſeuenth booke of the warre of the Iewes, the fower <hi>Attiques</hi> amountyng to xiiij. Frenche Souſes, after three Souſes and ſixe Frenche pence for a Souſe, as muche as the Romaine penie, as writeth lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Budaeus</hi> in his booke <hi>De Aſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When you haue thus diſpoſed your Henne houſes, and made them ſure and ſaffe againſte all hurtfull beaſtes and vermine, that maie enter by Daie or Night, and haue well
<pb facs="tcp:982:5"/>placed the Panyars, to receiue and harbour theim, you ſhall beſtowe the ſomme of three hundreth Frankes, in buiyng of good Hennes, whiche maie coſte you after the rate of fiue Souſes (whiche is ſixe pence and twoo thirdes) the peece, by reaſon of the dearth whiche is now,<note place="margin">xxv. Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks iv. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vj. d. &amp; ij. thirdes of j. d.</note> by occaſion of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Whiche ſhalbe twelue hundreth Hennes, after fiue and twentic Frankes the hundred.</p>
            <p>The Countries of Angeou, Touraine, and Lodunoys, haue been the countries with Britaigne, leſſe troubled with the ſaid Ciuill warres: and therefore Hennes are there bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cheape: Alſo verie good, ſtrong, well membred, and of the beſte race to make your emploite.</p>
            <p>You ſhall chooſe the yongeſt, whiche are apter to laye then the old: And the cammo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, more then thei of kinde: or the Blacke, Redde, and Taunie, whiche are more fruitfull then the Graie or White, as <hi>Aristotle</hi> affirmeth in his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of beaſtes in the firſt booke, the firſte Chapiter. And alſo thei whiche haue their creaſte or combe double and vpright, as witneſſeth <hi>Plinie</hi> in his naturall Hiſtorie. Alſo <hi>Palladius</hi> and <hi>Petrus Creſcencis</hi> in his booke of Houſebandrie. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Carolus Stephanus</hi> a man of our tyme, and a diligent gatherer of thynges Economike, parteinyng to Houſholde and Houſebandrie.</p>
            <p>Thei of a meane bigneſſe, are the beſte, hauyng their breaſt large, their bodie well fleſhed, not with long ſpurres like vnto Cockes, for thei commonly breake their Egges. Take heede alſo that thei be not to fatte. Witneſſe the good wife, whiche beyng in loue with her Henne, fed her ſo well, and made her ſo fat, that ſhe left laiyng, as rehearſeth <hi>Eſope</hi> in his Fables.</p>
            <p>You ought to thinke, that the good woman loued her Henne no leſſe, then the Emperour <hi>Honorius,</hi> Soonne of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> loued his, named Rome. Who vnderſtandyng that <hi>Alaricus</hi> kyng of the Gothes had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome (whiche
<pb facs="tcp:982:6"/>was the auncient Citie of Rome) was verie ſad, ſuppoſyng that <hi>Alaricus</hi> had taken his Henne, whiche he ſo mutche loued, as <hi>Zonar</hi> the Greeke Hiſtoriographer hath written, in the life of <hi>Honorius.</hi> I ſaie the aunciente Rome, becauſe the Emperours of the Eaſt partes, called Conſtantinople, newe Roome.</p>
            <p>In like maner you ſhall buye Cockes, to ſort or matche them: ſixe ſcore Cockes ſhall ſuffice for the twelue hundreth Hennes.<note place="margin">v. li. vi. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. viij. d.</note> For one Cocke, maie ſuffice for ten Hennes. Thei maie coſte you tenne Souſes the peece, ouer and aboue the price of the Hennes: whiche amounteth to xlviij. Frankes. Thei of the age from a yere and a halfe, vnto twoo yeres, are the beſte.</p>
            <p>To knowe them well, you ſhall conſider the Plumage, or Feathers. The Blacke, Red, and Taunie, are the beſte. Alſo thei that haue their Combe or Creaſte vpright, and double, or diuided. Their eyes redde and gliſteryng: Their becke, ſhorte and hooked: well ſpurred: their goyng, hautie and proude: Their voice ſtrong and ſoundyng: and ſutche as crowe mutche, repreſentyng ſutche a Maieſtie, as did the Cocke of the Perſians, whiche emong them was reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and honoured for a kyng, as reciteth <hi>Aristophanes.</hi> At the leaſt, that thei ſhewe a certaine hardineſſe, as thei which the <hi>Carians,</hi> people of the leſſe <hi>Aſia,</hi> bore vppon their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion or Helmet, goyng to battaill: as <hi>Alexander de Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xandro</hi> hath written in the xx. Chapiter of his firſt booke.</p>
            <p>And if you will take pleaſure in Diuination of thynges to come by Cockes,<note place="margin">Alectoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantia,</note> (whiche Diuination is named <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoromantia</hi>) as did <hi>Iamblicus</hi> maiſter of <hi>Proclus,</hi> as <hi>Liba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> his companion, great and learned Philoſophers, in the tyme of the Emperour <hi>Valens,</hi> you maie make experimente of ſutche predictions, and therewith dooe pleaſure to your freendes.</p>
            <p>And to the ende that you ſhall not bee ignoraunte in the
<pb facs="tcp:982:6"/>Theorike, or Speculation of the ſaied Diuination, I will ſhewe you a certaine practiſe and Prognoſtication thereof. Certaine greate lordes were curious to knowe, who ſhould bee ſucceſſour to the Empire, after <hi>Valens,</hi> fauourer of the damnable ſect of the Arrians: praiyng theſaid Philoſophers to giue aunſwere, accordyng to their Arte and experience, whiche thei had of ſutche thinges. Who were verie diligent to ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fie their requeſt, as commonly men of letters are not ingrate to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate to others, the fruites of their garden.</p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>Iamblicus,</hi> and <hi>Libanius,</hi> choſe a place verie plaine and equall, of conueniente largeneſſe: and cauſed fine pouder, or aſhes to bee ſifted therein. In the whiche pouder, thei wrote the xxiiij. letters of the Alphabet equally diſtante the one from the other, one little cubite a ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der, whiche is a foote and a halfe.</p>
            <p>The xxiiij. Letters ſo written and ordered, made a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure pentagon, or of fiue angles, hauyng fiue equall diſtances: Vpon euery of the whiche letters, thei laied tenne graines, one of Wheate, and an other of Barley.</p>
            <p>The Figure beyng ſet in order, thei tooke a Cocke, and ſaied to hym theſe woordes: Cocke enuious, Cocke ielous, Cocke proude: Eate the graine, and leaue the letter. Then makyng a greate whiſperyng, in maner of a Charme, thei lett the Cocke ſo Charmed, eate certaine of the graines liyng vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the letters. The which letters the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ioyned together, and ſette in order, accordyng to the graines whiche laye on them, theſe letters were founde. <hi>T, H, E, O, D.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod.</note> And were thereby contented to ſearche no further.</p>
            <p>And by this Diuination by the Cocke, the ſaied Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers gaue aunſwere, that the ſucceſſour of the Empire, ſhould be one <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> or <hi>Theodorus,</hi> or <hi>Theodotus,</hi> wher of <hi>Valens</hi> beyng aduertiſed, was greatly diſpleaſed, fearyng leaſt his children ſhould bee depriued of the Empire. And therefore putte to death all the greate Lordes, whiche were
<pb facs="tcp:982:7"/>ſo named. <hi>Iamblicus</hi> had euill fortune, and ſhortly after was poiſoned. <hi>Vopiſcus, Lampridius,</hi> and <hi>Zonare,</hi> whiche haue written the liues of the Emperours of the Eaſt and Weſt, will make you wiſe in this Prognoſtication.</p>
            <p>Not without reaſon I haue rehearſed vnto you this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Cubite. For if your figure Pentagon, were directed by the greate Cubite (whiche is of nine foote, accordyng to the whiche, the Arke of Noe was meaſured, as ſome Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latours haue affirmed) you might faile in your Diuination, and ſhall not come to the knowledge of that your deſire.</p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, for aſmuche as ſutche Diuinations, bee deceiptes, and enchauntmentes of the eyes and ſenſes, hauyng in them no ſubſtaunce of truthe, but rather of lyes, you ſhall giue no faithe thereto. For falſhoode is euer ouercome by truthe: as by example allegorike, <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his Hiſtorie of the Antiquitie of the Iewes, in the ſecond booke and fifte Chapiter declareth: As alſo is written in Exodus, Chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeuen. Where the rodde of Moiſes, was by the finger of God tourned into a very Serpent, and deuoured the phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtike Serpentes of the Magicians of Pharaa. And the Aucthours of the ſaied Magique, finally receiued their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde as did <hi>Iamblicus:</hi> and as did <hi>Arphaxat</hi> the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian of Perſia, who was ſtriken with a Thunderbolte: As was alſo the Bailife of <hi>Maſcon,</hi> whom the Deuill carried awaie, as our Chronicles witneſſeth. And alſo as wer <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetin</hi> and <hi>Hollere,</hi> Magicians of the Gothes, whiche were ouerwhelmed, as writeth <hi>Olaus Magnus</hi> in his Hiſtorie of the North Regions, in the third booke. Likewiſe <hi>Oddo</hi> a Magician of Demnarke, who was drouned. And infinite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers came to the like euill ende.</p>
            <p>But now to retourne to our He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes: To entreate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and gouerne them well, you muſt haue fower ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes or mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, with large eares, well to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue, and vnderſtande your commaundementes: and the feete of Hartes, with diligente
<pb facs="tcp:982:7"/>expeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to execute the ſame: and a truſtie right hande to be faithfull, loiall, obedient, and of fewe wordes. For (as ſaieth the <hi>Terentian Parmenio</hi>) it is a greate faulte in ſeruauntes to bee babbelers, and not to keepe their Maiſters counſaill.</p>
            <p>Their office ſhalbe to bryng the Hennes into their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes euery daie, at fiue of the clocke in the Euenyng in Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: and at three of the clocke in Winter. Alſo that thei bee diligent to cloſe the entries, and windowes of the Hen hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that in the night the Foxe (naturall enemie to Hennes) Weaſelles, or Polecattes, maie haue no acceſſe. And in the mornyng, to open the entries and windowes, that thei may come forthe. And then to make cleane the Pearches and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Alſo to refreaſhe their Pottes and Troughes with cleane water. For filthie and corrupt water, engendreth the pippe, and other ſickneſſes.</p>
            <p>In the daie alſo, the ſaied ſeruauntes muſt be myndfull to viſite the Panyers, if thei be furniſhe with Haye, and to refreſhe them if neede bee. The whiche muſt be doen euery weeke, for engenderyng of Liſe, Wormes, and Vermine, whiche make the Hennes leane, and cauſe them to ſcratche.</p>
            <p>In like maner thei muſt hee diligente, in gatheryng the Egges. And by accompt to deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a woman, whiche ſhall lay them in order vpon faire wheate ſtrawe, in a place of large and free ayre, to be kept freaſhe and cold. The ſame ſeruantes, after that in the Mornyng, thei haue giuen them their feedyng of Barly and Otes, and ſometymes alſo Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or Tares, ſhall caſte emong them ſome drie Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounge, to the ende that the Hennes maie labour the more, to ſearche their meate with ſcrapyng. For ſutche exerciſe, is wholſome for them. Then aboute Noone, thei ſhall feede them againe, callyng them with loude voice, that thei maie be acquainted with the call of their keepers, whom thei will ſone knowe, as did the Sparrowe of <hi>Leſbia Catullma:</hi> The Parrat of <hi>Corinna Ouidiana:</hi> The Thruſtle of <hi>Agrippina</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:982:8"/>the wife of the Emperoure <hi>Claudius:</hi> The Rauen of the Shoomaker of Romme, whiche gaue the good morowe to the Emperours <hi>Liberius, Germanicus,</hi> and <hi>Druſus.</hi> And was bought for twentie <hi>Sesterns,</hi> amounting to the ſomme of fiue hundred crounes of our money, by the ſupputation of <hi>Budaeus,</hi> after the rate of fiue and twentie Crounes one <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterne.</hi> And in like maner ſhall thei dooe a little before thei bryng them to rouſte.</p>
            <p>If your yarde containe twoo Acres incloſed, you maye thereof Plowe halfe an Acre in ſome corner, where the He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes maie ſometymes in the daie ſcrape the ground, and to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them ſelues in the duſte or ſande, wherein thei take great pleaſure. You ſhall Plowe or hardell the ſaied lande, once in the Moneth, that it become not too harde, that the Hennes maie eaſily raiſe it, without hurtyng their clawes.</p>
            <p>You maie alſo caſte certaine ſeedes vppon the Plowed ground, and couer it with the hardell, that the Hennes maie take bothe more pleaſure and labour, in diſcoueryng it. For the Hennes through idelneſſe, become groſſe and heauie, and will ceaſe from laiyng.</p>
            <p>When your Houſbandrie ſhalbe thus well ordered, you muſt practiſe in the Citie of Paris, with ten or twelue Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, dwellyng in ſondrie places of the ſaied Citie. Not of the beardleſſe and delicate Apollinaries, whiche care for nothyng but glorie, and ciuill flatterie, to gett riche wiues. But of the bearded <hi>Aeſculapians,</hi> ſuche as was the famous Florentine, a man of ſinguler knowledge, and experience in his art, and famous for the wiſe counſaill whiche he gaue to his daughter, purſued by the vnchaſte loue of <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> kyng of Naples and Hungarie.</p>
            <p>Sutche auncient Phiſitions, will eaſily permitt the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of Nature, and confirme the wholeſome Edicte of the Emperour <hi>Claudius:</hi> who (as witneſſeth <hi>Suetonius</hi>) permitted in banquettes and companies, freely and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:982:8"/>ſhame, to let ſcape the winde of the beallie, knowyng that certaine ſhamefaſte perſones, ſubiecte to the Collicke, haue died for holdyng the ſaied ventoſitie: As alſo <hi>Cicero</hi> in the xxij. booke of his Epiſtles, ſaith that fartyng ought to be as free as belchyng, after the opinion of the Stoikes.</p>
            <p>You ſhall giue theim to vnderſtande, that you can daiely furniſhe their Pacientes with newe laied Egges, euery mornyng without faile. You ſhall alſo aduertiſe theim, of theim that haue the ſellyng, and diſtribution of them.</p>
            <p>You ſhall alſo take heede, that you haue not to deale with ſuche Phiſitions, whiche haue nought els to doe theim to walke their Mules, as thei were whiche were obſerued by Maiſter <hi>Francis Rables Pentagruell,</hi> to departe out of their lodgyng at ſixe of the clocke in the mornyng, and to returne at Noone without ſtrikyng of ſtroke. For ſuche are the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie pacientes of impacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, by the vnderſtandyng of <hi>Epop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques</hi> and <hi>Acromatiques</hi> of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> his Diſciple, whiche thei thought onely worthie to bee read, as writeth <hi>Quintus Curtius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In like maner you muſt bee acquainted with xv. or xx. Gainſellers, or Regraters, ſuche as can chatte and babble beſte, and walke aboute all the ſtreates, and the fower cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Citée, and the moſte famous places of the ſame: as the Burſe, the Pallaice, the greate Haules, the Portes, and other places of greate reſorte: Aſſuryng theim to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe them daiely of a number of newe laied Egges, which thei ſhall ſell and diſtribute to your profite, agreeyng with theim for reaſonable price and wages, as ſhalbe ſaied here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>Hauyng kepe this order, you ſhall bee carefull and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, to cauſe your Egges daiely to bee caried to the Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſters, or women that ſhall ſell them againe in the morning of the daie followyng. You maie carie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſte vpon Aſſes. For whiche purpoſe, that Beaſte is very proper, becauſe of
<pb facs="tcp:982:9"/>his ſlowe goyng, that he breake not the Egges. But take heede that thei eate no Figges, leaſte you bruſte for laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng, as did the Philoſopher <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> as writeth <hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Laertius,</hi> in his booke of the liues of Philoſophers. The like alſo chaunced to <hi>Philomenes,</hi> as writeth <hi>Valerius Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus,</hi> in his Chapiter of rare kyndes of Death.</p>
            <p>Now it reſteth to make you vnderſtande the profite, that ſhall come vnto you daiely of your ſumme: all charges and expenſes deducted: the rent of your houſe paied, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of your ſeruauntes, the Gainſellers conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Aſſe, his keeper compted, and alſo the graine or corne wherewith your Hennes are fedde. For of the ſale of Egges, is taken no cuſtome, or impoſition, as was in the tyme of Ihon <hi>Ducas</hi> Emperour of Conſtantinople, and ſucceſſour of <hi>Theodoſius Laſcaris,</hi> who was ſo exceſſiue, that in a few daies, the Croune of <hi>Irene</hi> the Empreſſe, was thereby marueilouſly enriched in precious ſtones and ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welles, as <hi>Nephorius</hi> hath left in writing, in the third booke of the Hiſtorie <hi>Bizantine,</hi> in the chapiter, of the famine of the Turkes.</p>
            <p>You ſhall ſell, or cauſe to be ſolde, euery new laied egge eaſely for ſixe Frenche pence the peece. For I aſſure you, that within the Citee of Paris, are a thouſande, yea rather twoo thouſande, that will gladly giue a Carolus (whiche is nyne Frenche pence) for euery newe laied Egge, beyng thereof aſſured: wherein ſee you faile not.</p>
            <p>Howe many Gentlemen and Gentlewomen are there, whiche greatly deſire in the Mornyng, to eate a newe laied Egge? How many are there of Citezins, and their wiues, touched with the like deſire: How many olde folkes wearie of Fleſhe, could for their Dinner bee contente, with a newe laied Egge or twoo? For you muſt knowe that an Egge, is naturally of good nouriſhemente, wholſome, delicate, of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie digeſtion, and maketh good bloud, as writeth <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:982:9"/>Aphrodiſeus</hi> in his ſeconde booke, and xxviij. queſtion of his Problemes. Likewiſe <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> writeth, that an Egge engendereth in a man, as muche good blood, as is the bigneſſe of the yolke, whiche tourneth almoſte all into bloud.</p>
            <p>I haue yet made no memorie of ſicke folkes, whiche of neceſſitie haue nede of new laied Egges, by the ordinaunce of the Phiſitions, whoſe freendſhip you ſhall entertaine for the ſame purpoſe. The number of the whiche ſicke folkes, I am ſure in the ſaied Citee, will daiely ſurmounte a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande perſones without ſpeakyng of them that keepe a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain diet, as well to encreaſe the luſtes of their pleaſures in Venerie, as alſo to reſtore that which ſomtyme by exceſſiue wantonneſſe, thei haue diminiſhed of their ſtrengthe and health. For theſe alſo ſhall haue neede of your marchandize.</p>
            <p>You maie therefore by this deduction, be aſſured of the vent and ſale, and deliueraunce of your Egges daie by daie as muche as your Hennes ſhall doe their endeuour, orderly to furniſhe your Cuſtomers.</p>
            <p>Now lette vs retourne to our accompt. You can gather no leſſe euery daie of your xij. hundreth Hennes, then eight hundreth Egges: whiche are twoo terces or thirde partes of the number: Leauyng the other terce or thirde parte of your Hennes, in the meane tyme to reſte and repoſe theim ſelues. For the ſeaſon is not euery daie agreable for all He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to laye: Specially in the middeſt of Winter, and other tymes neare vnto that. But you ſhall then helpe them in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng them Fenegreke, commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly called the dredge of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And alſo Barly halfe ſodde. For theſe thinges keepe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in naturall heate, and cauſe them to laye.<note place="margin">L. Souſes v. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vi. d. and ii. third par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of a peny xliiij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. v. d. ij. thirdes.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Eight hundreth Egges, by ſupputation Arithemeticall, at ſixe Frenche pence the peece, will yeld. L. Souſes for the hundreth. Which in number producte, maketh xx. Frankes or Frenche poundes a daie. Whiche is, for the ſaied eight
<pb facs="tcp:982:10"/>hundreth, ſeuen ſcore Frankes the weeke, and ſeuen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande three hundreth Frankes the yeare, of honeſt profite.</p>
            <p>Let vs diuiſe the charges. And that whiche then remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, wee will call the gaines and profite. For the Lawiers ſaie, that wee call nothyng profite, ſauyug what remaineth after the charges deducted: as the famous Lawier <hi>Papinia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> hath well defined in the xxiiij. booke of the Pandectes, vnder the title of repetition of dowrie after the mariage diſſolued.</p>
            <p>Firſte for the penſion of the woorke man,<note place="margin">ij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ii. d. and ii. thirdes.</note> and his Houſe for euery daie twentie Souſe: whiche by the yere commeth to three hundreth, three ſcore and fiue Frankes. I here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande yeres of the Sunne conſiſting of three hundreth, three ſcore and fiue daies.</p>
            <p>For fower Seruauntes or maides, twentie Souſes the daie, which is for eche of them for wages, meate and drinke, fiue Souſes to finde them ſelues:<note place="margin">xl. li. xi. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. d. &amp; i. third</note> amountyng in the yere to the like ſumme of three hundreth three ſcore and fiue Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. You knowe how greately ſobrietie is to bee commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in ſeruauntes, both men and women: which kicke when thei bee fatte (as doe Monkes in the mewe) and murmure when thei be full. Emong the whiche, wee meane not ſuche as with pure conſcience, exerciſe them ſelues in their vowe of contemplation of Diuine thynges, in whoſe ſoules, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation taketh perfection, as ſaieth the Diuines. For in all ſortes of men, the beſte ought to bee reſpected, and the worſt noted. Neither yet doe I meane, that you ſhould bee ſparyng for the meate of your ſeruauntes, as was the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of Poſon in Hungarie, who was wont to ſaie that of all the workes of his ſeruauntes, the mouyng of their Iawes greeued him moſte: he was ſo filthis coueteous, that he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to ſee his ſeruauntes eate, as writeth <hi>Aeneas Sylui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in the xlij. Chapiter of his Hiſtorie of Boheme.</p>
            <p>For the charges of the twoo Aſſes (although Thiſtles growe euery where aboundantly) we will allowe fiue Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:982:10"/>a daie: amountyng to fower ſcore and tweltie Frankes,<note place="margin">vi. d. and ij. thirdes. x. li. v. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> and fiue Souſes in the yere. And for the Aſſe keper (whom you maie alſo applie too other ſeruice, after that hee hath brought his Egges to the place appointed (who can haue no leſſe then one maide to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panie hym, whoſe allowance beyng after the rate of fiue Souſes the daie, commeth to fower ſcore and twelue Franks, and fiue Souſes the yere. Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhall aduertiſe, that he ouercharge not his Aſſes leaſt thei murmure as doe the Monkes vnreformed.</p>
            <p>The Emperour <hi>Augustus Caeſar</hi> after the victorie <hi>Actium</hi> againſt <hi>Antonius,</hi> iniured by the loue of <hi>Cleopatrae</hi> Queene of Egipte, goyng to ſee the ſhippes captiue, found ſodainly an Aſſe-keper, and aſked him what was his name: Who aunſwered that his name was <hi>Fortunatus:</hi> and the names of his Aſſes, <hi>Victorious.</hi> Thereby gratulatyng the victorie of the Emperor. You maie feele the profite of your Aſſes with like congratulation, and hope of good Fortune and victorie, againſt them that woulde haue throwen you into miſerable pouertie: if you followe your buſineſſe with requiſite diligence as did the ſaied Emperour <hi>Augustus</hi> his warres: Auoidyng ſuche delices and pleaſures, as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius</hi> vſed with <hi>Cleopatra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For meate or feedyng for the Hennes, ſhall ſuffice for the daie twoo quarters of Paris meaſure, as well in Barly as in Otes, Fitches, or Tares: and in Winter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Septier</hi> is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Quarter of Paris v. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vi. d. and ij. thirdes.</note> bearde or horned Wheate, (whiche in Champaigne is called Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine Wheate) after xxv. Souſes the Septier or quarter, whiche by the daie amounteth to L. Souſes: and in the yere ſeuen hundreth, fower ſcore and ſeuen Frankes, and tenne Souſes, whiche is fower ſcore and vij. li. x. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>As touchyng the Phiſitians, ſome of theim ſelues ſhall haue neede of your marchandiſe: as thei that haue a Fame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and many little children: whom you muſt viſite weekely with certaine quarterons of newe laied Egges, brought on
<pb facs="tcp:982:11"/>Thurſdaie for Fridaie and Saterdaie. At Eaſter alſo with certaine Red Egges to preſent to their neighbours, as the reuenue of their practike. But ſuche as haue no familie, and ſeke for wife and houſe, followyng the precepte of <hi>Xenophon</hi> in his <hi>Oeconomiques,</hi> you maie to (gratifie them) ſhewe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the increaſe of your Houſebandry, and recite vnto them the pleaſure whiche you receiue therein, to haſten them to caſte theim ſelues into the nette of happie Miſhap, and yet in the meane tyme honour them with ſome pretie Preſentes.</p>
            <p>And if you haue the meanes to recouer Pullettes, or Chickens of the race of the He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, which engendereth them perfectly formed, ſcrapyng and pepyng, and followyng the Henne, as ſone as thei bee out of the Egge (as rehearſeth <hi>Apuleius</hi> in his booke of the golden Aſſe) you maie thereby giue argument of high Philoſophie of noueltees, vpon the doubte whiche thei make, if the round Egges bryng forthe Cockes, and the long Egges Hennes. Wherein <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> the Ape of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> doeth contrary his Maiſter, in the ſixth booke of Beaſtes.</p>
            <p>But in the reſolution of this queſtion, you ſhall finde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no leſſe troubled,<note place="margin">A pretie queſtion.</note> then in this: whiche is, why there are moe Sheepe then Wolues: Seyng that one Sheepe common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engendereth not but one, or ſeldome tymes two, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Wolfe bryngeth forthe eight or nyne. Againe, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration that for one Wolfe that is killed, a thouſande or twoo thouſande Sheepe goe to the ſlaughter. For the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whiche <hi>Herodotus</hi> bryngeth in his thirde booke of his Muſe of <hi>Thalia,</hi> (where he ſaieth, that Nature hath made fierce and cruell Beaſtes more fruitfull, ſpeakyng of the multitude of Serpentes and Vipers, whiche in <hi>Arabia</hi> keepe the Trees of Frankenſence (can not bee applied to Wolues, whiche are fierce and rauenyng. But to retourne to our charges.</p>
            <p>For the entertainemente of the ſaied Phiſitians, I giue
<pb facs="tcp:982:11"/>you eſtate of twoo hundred and three ſcore Frankes by the yere.<note place="margin">xxviij. li. xvii. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ix d. one thirde.</note> So ſhall your Phiſitians haue no occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, that thei haue the penſion of Pulters. Of other fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie neuertheleſſe, that he that is founde culpable of falſe reporte, ſhall abide the Iudgement of the Senatour <hi>Papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> at the ſiege of <hi>Aquilon,</hi> a Toune of the <hi>Samnites,</hi> of the whiche <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius Maximus</hi> maketh mention in his ſeuenth booke.</p>
            <p>To the Gainſellers,<note place="margin">vi. d. and ij. thirdes. xv. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. vi. d. ij. thirdes. xl. li. xi. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. d. and i. thirde.</note> you ſhall giue fiue Souſes for a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> charge, that thei ſell not in your name, any Egges but yours. Whiche in ſumme, ſhalbe by the weeke ſeuen Frankes: and by the yere, three hundred, three ſcore and fiue Frankes. In the whiche you ſhall doe nothyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the opinion of <hi>Socrates,</hi> who blamed theim that bought Marchaundize by groſſe, to ſell theim againe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by retaile, as hurtfull to the common wealthe.</p>
            <p>Then the ſupputation or compte beyng made vppon xx. Frankes of the ſale of your Egges by the daie,<note place="margin">x. li. iiij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. v. d. one thirde. viij. hundred vi. li. ij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ij. d. ij. thirdes. three hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred li. vij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ij. d. ij. thirdes.</note> amountyng to ſeuen thouſande and three hundred Frankes by the yere, wee muſte rebate the ſumme of twoo thouſande, ſeuen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and three Frankes, and fiue Souſes Tournois, (of currante money) for the expenſes here before compted. So remaineth vnto you the profite by the yere, the ſumme of fower thouſande, fiue hundreth, fower ſcore and xvj. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and fiue Souſes, whiche is fiue hundreth and xj. li. xiij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. x. d. and ij. thirdes.</p>
            <p>And when your laiyng Hennes ſhalbe no more then ſixe C. a daie, leauyng the other ſixe C. in reſt to abide their ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet ſhall remaine vnto you xv. Frankes by the daie: and by the yere, iii. M. iiii. C. xlvii. Frankes, three Souſes,<note place="margin">xxxiij. s<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. iiii. d.</note> and ix. pence, all charges deducted, whiche amounteth to three hundreth fower ſcore and three li. v. d.</p>
            <p>Which ſeemeth to me an honeſt gaine and profite, vpon the emploiyng of ſo little a ſumme, and that, without all fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
<pb facs="tcp:982:12"/>Vſurie: By the meanes alſo whereof, your maie feaſte your freendes, and leade a ioyfull life: I ſaie not prodigall, as of <hi>Aſope</hi> the <hi>Tragike,</hi> with his platter of ſmall birdes, whereof <hi>Plinie</hi> maketh mention in the tenth booke of his Naturall Hiſtorie. Neither ſo daintie or gluttonous as of <hi>Apitius,</hi> that was in the tyme of the Emperour <hi>Tiberius.</hi> Neither yet ſo ſumptuous and magnificent, as that of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullus</hi> noted of <hi>Plutarche</hi> (in his booke of the liues of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous men) for the banket whiche he made vpon the ſodain, for <hi>Pompeius</hi> and <hi>Cicero:</hi> the expenſe whereof was no leſſe then twelue hundred and fiftie Crounes, commyng to fiftie <hi>Sesternes</hi> Romaine. Or that of <hi>Pomponius Atticus.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain on the other parte, I meane not that your liuyng ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bee ſo ſtreight, in frugalitie or ſparyng, as was that of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Dentatus,</hi> who liued with Radiſhe rootes. Or of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinax,</hi> who would bee ſerued tenne tymes with one Salet. Neither ſo vile or ſparyng, as was <hi>Epaminondas</hi> a greate Lorde of <hi>Thebes,</hi> who kept his chamber while his apparell was amendyng, becauſe he would haue no chaunge.</p>
            <p>But temperate and modeſte, as that of the Kynges of Egipte, who before thei fell too their meate, diſputed of modeſtie and ſobrietie, takyng pleaſure in bankettes, more ioyfull, then ſumptuous or exquiſite. And ſo ſhall you not fall into the penaltie of the Lawe Numerall of <hi>Iulius,</hi> who prefined a Taxe to bee paied of the charges, made in greate feaſtes and bankettes.</p>
            <p>And for as muche as it maie ſeme a thyng vndecente, that a man ſhould make profeſſion of an Arte, or trafique of Marchandize, whereof he hath no knowledge, beyng igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the natures and temperatures of the thinges, which he hath in hande: I will not faile to aduertiſe you of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, whiche come to Hennes and Cockes, and of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and when it ſhalbee needefull to chaunge them, and put others in their places, to the ende that your number doe
<pb facs="tcp:982:12"/>not diminiſhe: as you knowe that by ſurrogation, the kindes of all thynges are preſerued in their beyng, and ſo remaine perpetually, as diuine <hi>Diotimus</hi> taught <hi>Socrates</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond booke of the feaſt of <hi>Plato.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their common diſeaſe is the pippe, whiche is a diſeaſe of the tongue, the ende whereof is thereby hardened, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of a griſtle. And thereby alſo the Henne loſeth her taſt, bothe in eatyng and drinkyng: and infecteth alſo the other Hennes, ſpecially within the houſe, and the place of their feedyng.</p>
            <p>This diſeaſe proceedeth, either of beeyng long without drinckyng of cleane and freaſhe water, or by drinckyng of foule and ſtinckyng water. And to heale it, you muſte take the Henne, and take awaie the ſuperfluitie, whiche groweth on the tong hardened at the ende. And then waſhe the tong and beake with oyle, in the whiche ſhalbe tempered a hedde of Garlike. And put emong their meate Stapheſacre: and to rubbe the tong well with Spettle or Vineger, firſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered in the mouthe of the ſeruaunt.</p>
            <p>An other diſeaſe, is the Catare or Rheume, whiche is a fluxion of cold humours in the hed of the Heaues, making them to hang their winges, and their Creaſtes or combes. The remedie is, to trauerſe or ouerthwart their noſethrells with a Feather putte through them, to open the Fluxion or Rheume that is ſtopped, and maketh them blinde. It ſhall alſo be good to warme their drinke in Winter: becauſe ſuch diſeaſes proceede of cold, or drinkyng of Froſen water, or liyng vnder the Moone, the mother of all moiſtueſſe.</p>
            <p>Againſt the Lice and Vermine, whiche maketh them leane, feeble, and vnfruitfull, I haue ſhewed you the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. But when the diſeaſe is now come, the remedie is too bathe them with a little wine, or drinke, in the whiche ſhall be ſodden ſome Comine, or Staphiſacre, commonly called the death of Lice, appliyng it to the heddes of little children,
<pb facs="tcp:982:13"/>with ointmentes.</p>
            <p>If you doubte, how I knowe this, not alledgyng any Authour for the proofe: you ſhall vnderſtande that I haue learned it, by practize of the common people, in like maner as the wiſemen emong the Hebrues, named <hi>Cabalistae,</hi> and the like emong the Gaules named <hi>Druydes,</hi> learned their Sciences by Tradition, from mouthe to mouthe, and from hande to hande without letters. Wherby is come to paſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in our Fraunce, the gouernment is more by cuſtomes not written, then by written lawes: as <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> hath writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his Commentaries, of the conqueſt of the Gaules or Frenchemen, in his ſixt Booke.</p>
            <p>The auncientes haue written certaine remeadies, to keepe the Hennes from the Foxe, as <hi>Palladius</hi> in his booke of Houſebandrie, teacheth how to rubbe the walles of the Henne houſe, with the gaule of a Foxe, and to cutte in little peeces the fleſhe of a Foxe, and to mingle it with the Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes meate, to cauſe the Foxe to abhorre to come neare it, by feelyng the death of his proper kinde, whiche nature can not abide, as <hi>Plinie</hi> writeth in his nine and twentie booke of his Naturall Hiſtorie. But the moſte ſoueraigne remeadie, is to keepe faſt and cloſe the dores and windowes in the night. And that in the daie, your ſeruauntes often tymes come, and go in all places and corners of your cloſe. And that nere vnto it, or the Henne houſe, bee no heapes of wood, buſhes, or ſtones, where ſuche beaſtes maie be hidde or harboured. For, the beaſtes whiche liue by rapte, haue euer a certaine feare ioyned with their craftineſſe, and deſire of rauenyng.</p>
            <p>About the tyme of Autumne, you ſhall euery yere draw a hundred or twoo hundred of the eldeſt of your He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, and ſuche as haue their clawes longeſt, and groſſeſt. In place of the whiche, you ſhall put yonger of ſuche ſort or qualitie, As I haue before deſcribed.</p>
            <p>If peraduenture you bee of opinion, to keepe your Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:982:13"/>of one ſeaſon for an other, you muſt laye them in order vpon ſheaues of ſtrawe verie freaſhe, with the ſharpe ende vpwarde, or to laye theim in Panyers in like maner. And that thei be well couered with ſtrawe, that thei be not tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by too muche heate, or colde. And if you will chooſe the beſt for your frendes, take <hi>Candida, Longa, Noua</hi> (that is) white, long, and new, followyng the opinion of the ſchoole of <hi>Salerne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other twoo Acres whiche remaine aboute youre Yarde, Courte, or place encloſed, ſhall bee commodious to ſowe Barlie, whiche is a graine verie proper for the nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Hennes. And if you can recouer Barlie of the ſeede of <hi>Aethiope,</hi> whereas dwell the Iewes of the ligne of <hi>Dan, Nepthalin, Gad,</hi> and <hi>Aſſer,</hi> nere to the riuer of <hi>Sabbatique</hi> (whiche <hi>Moiſes</hi> affirmeth to be the riuer in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture called <hi>Goſan</hi>) it ſhalbe ſinguler good, becauſe one grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thereof bryngeth foorthe an hundred, as <hi>Eldad Damus</hi> the Hebrue hath written in his breef Hiſtorie of the Empire of the Iewes, incloſed in <hi>Aethiope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will write vnto you more ample of the other profites, whiche concerne the nouriture of Hennes, as of what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties thei are, and what one maie drawe of their ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But my ende hath been none other then to giue aduiſe, how for a little ſomme of money and little trauaile, you maie get greate profite: to the ende that you maie the more eaſily forgette your loſſes, and accuſtome your ſelf to the noyſe and cluckyng of your Hennes: and not to ſeeme more delicate, then was the good Philoſopher <hi>Socrates,</hi> who bore it eaſily becauſe thei laied hym Egges: as he bore paciently the murmuryng and ſcoldyng of his wife <hi>Xantippe,</hi> becauſe ſhe bore hym children.</p>
            <p>You maie euery daie ſe your menage or houſebandrie. And (as did the <hi>Peripatici</hi>) walke aboute the cloſes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places: and conſider the endeuour of your ſeruauntes.
<pb facs="tcp:982:14"/>Whom alſo by this meanes you ſhall make more carefull and diligent: and your Hennes better entreated, accordyng to the <hi>Apophthegme</hi> whiche ſaieth: That the eye of the Maiſter maketh the ſeruaunt prompter, and the Horſe fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: as alſo <hi>Aristotle</hi> maketh mention in his firſt booke of <hi>Oeconomikes.</hi> But how ſo euer it bee, directe your Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie in ſuche order, that bones be not giuen to Aſſes, and Thiſtles to Dogges.</p>
            <p>The Maid ſeruaunt or Chamberlaine, of <hi>Promotheus</hi> (named <hi>Experience</hi>) who ſerued hym, after that he had brought from Heauen the liberall Sciences, and to whom when he drue nere to death he gaue them by Teſtament, maie in ſhort tyme aſſure you, either to continue this Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize and traffique, or to leaue it. For ſhe (<hi>Experience</hi> I meane) is one of the cheef ſeruauntes whiche you muſte haue, with other diligent companie.</p>
            <p>You ought not to take it greeuouſſtie to leaue youre dwellyng place, and accuſtomed pleaſaunte Aire, or your neighbours, couſins, or freendes. For you knowe well the incommodities whiche Ciuill warre bryngeth, the whiche (as writeth <hi>Cicero</hi> to <hi>Marcus Marcellus,</hi> in the fourthe booke of his familier Epiſtles) is no leſſe lamentable, then the victorie gotten by ſheadyng of domeſticall blood. And therefore not without reaſon ſaieth the Prouerbe: That warre is pleaſaunte to ſuche as hath no experience thereof. The whiche ſaiyng <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> a rare manne in all kinde of learnyng hath in his <hi>Chiliades,</hi> dilated by many examples: as you maie alſo eaſily iudge at this preſent. You knowe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the Marchaunte to flie pouertie, hazardeth hym ſelf by lande and ſea, and leaueth his natiue aire and countrey.</p>
            <p>And for the doubt that you maie haue, not to be aſſured in peaceable poſſeſſion of your incloſed ground, againſt the violence of Theeues and ſoldiours: I would wiſhe you for the gard thereof, either the wakyng Serpent whiche kept
<pb facs="tcp:982:14"/>the garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of <hi>Heſpides</hi> (famous for the golden apples) ſlain by <hi>Hercules</hi> of <hi>Thebes,</hi> or the furious Bulles whiche kept the golden fleeſe in the Ile of <hi>Colchos,</hi> vnder the king <hi>Aoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> the father of <hi>Meda,</hi> whiche wer ouercome and taken by <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of <hi>Theſſalia,</hi> at the voiage of the <hi>Argonautae.</hi> Haue recourſe to the <hi>Metamorphoſes</hi> of <hi>Ouid</hi> in the fowerth and ſeuenth Booke. But better then all this ſhall ſerue for your ſecuritie, a tablet of three or fower flower de Lice (the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Seale) authorized by the kyng: whiche ſhalbe of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter efficacie then any other ſauegard that you can deſire.</p>
            <p>For finall counſaill, I praie you continewe in the loue and feare of God, obeiſaunce to your Prince and his Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, reuerence to all ſuperiours, with pacience of youre loſſes, to occupie your trade without fraude, and you ſhall finde multiplication of all your gooddes. And then (as ſaith <hi>Iuuenall</hi> in his thirde <hi>Satyre</hi>) you maie ſaie that you are ſonne of a white Henne.</p>
            <p>But when you ſhalbe knowne to doe ſeruice to ſo excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Common wealthe as is the Citee of Paris (whiche ſurmounteth all thoſe that haue been famous emong the Greekes) and that you haue giuen the firſte entrie, and (as ſaieth the Prouerbe) broken the Ice to others, I ſuppoſe your enemies ſhalbe repulſed, as were thei of <hi>Furius Creſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> Citezin of Roome enueighed of his neighbours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that of a little he raiſed more gaine, then thei did of muche tillage. For the whiche thei imputed vnto hym, that he vſed Witchcrafte, and Enchauntment. Who bryngyng for the his inſtrumentes of Houſebandrie, his diligente ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes: was diſcharged of all ſutche ſuſpicions, and of all menne greatly commended, as writeth <hi>Titus Liuius.</hi> And furthermore your felicitie and proſperitie, ſhalbee a paſſion to your enemies, as chaunceth to all enuious perſones.</p>
            <p>I knowe other experiences verie prompte. But of no greater gain then ſixe frankes the daie, all charges deducted
<pb facs="tcp:982:15"/>Therefore, if my firſt inſtructions ſeme not agreable vnto your Nature, aduertiſe me thereof, that I maie directe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you an other waie more eaſie, and no leſſe delectable, though of leſſe profite.</p>
            <p>Peraduenture ſome will thinke this Counſaile verie ſtraunge and ridiculous, and perhaps of difficult execution. To thinke it ſtraunge, there is no greater reaſon, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng the nouriſhyng of Hennes for honeſte gaines, is no newe or ſtraunge thyng, if we beleue that whiche <hi>Celius Rhodoginus,</hi> a worthie Authour, hath written in his fower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene booke of Antiquities: That in the Ile of <hi>Delos</hi> (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called <hi>Ortygia</hi> for the boundance of Quailes) beeyng one of the moſte famous of the <hi>Cyclades</hi> in the ſea <hi>Aegaeum</hi> were found many that made eſtate and traffike in the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhement of Hennes, for gaine and profite. Who were ſo well exerciſed herein, and in the knowledge of their He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, that onely vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſight of an Egge, thei could eaſily iudge what Henne it came from. Therefore, that ſellyng of Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hath euer been a thyng commonly vſed: haue recourſe to the Impoſt, whiche was in the tyme of the Emperour <hi>Honorius,</hi> as is ſaied heretofore.</p>
            <p>As touching mockers, no man can eſtabliſhe any thing ſo good or well ordered, that the mocker ſhall not bite, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Enuie hath made impreſſion in his fooliſhe brain, and hath there taken vp his lodgyng, to torment his hoſte.</p>
            <p>And to reſolue you of ſuche difficulties, let vs take hold of the ſaiyng of <hi>Agathon</hi> a yonge gentle man, in the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whiche he made of Loue, in the feaſte of <hi>Plato,</hi> ſaiyng: that we ought more to feare the iudgement of a fewe wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, then of many ignorant fooles and mockers. For wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menne ſlowlie giue the looſe bridle to their congues, but vſe their wordes with iudgement: as alſo writeth <hi>Cicero</hi> in his Oration for <hi>Plancius,</hi> ſaiyng: That the iudgement of tenne wiſe and graue men in one Citee, importeth more then the
<pb facs="tcp:982:15"/>iudgemente of all the common people, who for the moſte part iudge without counſaile or reaſon.</p>
            <p>If any man ſhall ſaie that the inuention of this counſell is olde: I confeſſe vnto you that I am not the firſte teacher hereof, as was <hi>Carbilius</hi> of the firſte letters at Rome, or the firſte Schoolemaiſter: yet hath it not been practized in our tyme. And as writeth the Poet <hi>Horatius.</hi> Many thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are renued whiche tyme hath deuoured, and buried as dedde, the whiche againe in tyme ſhalbe drouned in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of Obliuion, and ſhall againe retourne to their eſtate by courſe, as doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in maner all worldly thynges, as wiſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon alſo witneſſeth.</p>
            <p>Aſſure your ſelf my deare freede, that <hi>Magnifico Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret,</hi> or any other <hi>Alchemiste,</hi> haue not with their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces and Alembikes, drawne more profite by the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers ſtone, then you ſhall drawe out of the beally of your Hennes, if you will ioyne pleaſure with paine. And ſo ſhall you bee out of daunger, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whiche ſutche <hi>Alchemistes</hi> fall, who oftentymes conſume their Patrimonie, and blowe it awaie with bellowes. But euer beware the Foxe. In the meane tyme you ſhall receiue of your freend this little gift, ſuche as it is, in hope hereafter to recouer of hym ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thyng when occaſion doeth ſerue, whiche (occaſion) you muſt take by the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e before, that it ſcape not from you.</p>
            <p>Now therefore for the ende of this accompte, you muſt arme your ſelf with patience when affliction is ſent, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noide pouertie (the enemie of all good maners) by exerciſe of honeſte and profitable frugalitie in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yng the thynges, whiche you haue gotten by your labour: and therewith alſo a reputation not bulgare, whiche ſhalbe bruted through all Fraunce, for the noueltie of your enterpriſe. Whereof ſome will take ſuche pleaſure, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> moue the ſeuere <hi>Catoes</hi> to laughyng, and raiſe the Melancholike Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of weepyng <hi>Democrites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:982:16"/>And finally, you ſhall herewith receiue the contentation of your louyng freende with this pleaſaunt preſent, to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the forrowes of theſe cloudie tymes, and to putt you in good comfort of better hope in tyme to come.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Hatchyng of Egges without Hennes, as writeth Ioannes Porta in his ſecond booke of Magike Naturall.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ake the dounge of Pigeons or Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes beaten into pouder, and finely ſifted. Then laye the Egges in ſutche ſorte, that one touche not an other for breakyng. And ſee thei bee well coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the ſaied dounge bothe vnder and aboue, in cloſe Panyers or Coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes commodious for the purpoſe, ſo that the rounder or bigger ende of the Egges bee dounwarde. But firſte you muſte laye a bedde of Hennes feathers, and thereon the dounge: and likewiſe an other ranke or bedde of Feathers vpon the dounge that couereth the Egges. This doen, you ſhall euery fower and twentie howers tourne the Egges, that thei maie equally receiue the heate. Thei maie thus bee kepte, in a place of temperate heate. And when twentie daies are paſt, if you ſhall perceiue that the chickens ſtrike the ſhell with their billes, harken if thei peepe. For often it chaunceth, that for the thickneſſe of the ſkinne or filme, thei can not breake forth. Then helpe them with takyng of the Shell. And immediatly bryng the Henne vnto theim. The like maie be doen in a warme. Quen, tempered to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and proportion of Natural heate. Likewiſe alſo in hotte Horſe dounge, with like diligence of meaſuryng and conſeruyng of heate, with addyng of newe and pure doung
<pb facs="tcp:982:16"/>euery ſeuenth daie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cardanus</hi> in his twelueth booke <hi>De Subtilitate,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth mutche in like maner: But ſaieth that you muſte firſte make twoo Cuſſhions or Pillowes filled with Hennes dounge, beaten into fine pouder and Sifted. Then by ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng or other meanes, faſtenyng on the Pillowes Hennes Feathers bothe greate and ſmall of good thickeneſſe, and laye the Egges betwene theim in a warme place &amp;c. as before. He writeth that in the greate Citie of <hi>Alkair</hi> or <hi>Babilonia Noua</hi> in Egipt, thei vſe thus to hatche Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in greate mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
